<sections>

<section name="overview" title="Overview">
	<div class="section-docs">
	<p>
        SciSQL provides science-specific tools and extensions for SQL. Currently, the project
        contains user defined functions (UDFs) and stored procedures for MySQL in the areas
        of spherical geometry, statistics, and photometry. The project was motivated by the
        needs of the <a href="http://www.lsst.org/">Large Synoptic Survey Telescope</a> (LSST)
        and has been sponsored by LSST and <a href="http://slac.stanford.edu/">SLAC</a> /
        <a href="http://www.energy.gov/">DOE</a>. SciSQL is distributed under the terms of the
        <a href="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/lgpl.html">GNU Lesser General Public License v3</a>.
	</p>
	<ul>
	        <li><a href="https://launchpad.net/scisql">Official site</a></li>
	        <li><a href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/scisql/+filebug">Report a bug</a></li>
	        <li><a href="https://answers.launchpad.net/scisql/+addquestion">Ask a question</a></li>
	</ul>
	<p>
	The SciSQL documentation makes use of:
	</p>
	<ul>
		<li>
			<a href="http://jquery.com/">jQuery</a>, copyright John Resig and
			dual-licensed under the <a href="http://jquery.org/license/">MIT
			and GPL version 2 licenses</a>
		</li>
		<li>
			<a href="http://code.google.com/p/google-code-prettify/">Google prettify</a>,
			distriuted under the <a href="http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0">
			Apache License, Version 2.0</a>
		</li>
	</ul>
	</div>
</section>


<section name="install" title="Building &amp; Installation">
	<div class="section-docs">

	<h3>Prerequisites</h3>
	<dl>
		<dt><a href="http://www.python.org/download/">Python 2.5.x or later</a></dt>
		<dt><a href="http://dev.mysql.com/downloads/">MySQL server 5.x</a></dt>
		<dt><a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/mysql-python/">MySQLdb 1.2.x</a></dt>
		<dd>
			This is a Python DB API 2.0 implementation for MySQL,
			and is required when running the unit tests.
		</dd>
		<dt><a href="http://www.makotemplates.org/download.html">Mako</a></dt>
		<dd>
			The Mako templating system is only required for developers,
			and is used to build release documentation.
		</dd>
	</dl>
	<p>
	In order to install the UDFs, you will need write permission to the MySQL server
	plug-in directory, as well as a MySQL account with admin priviledges.
	</p>

	<h3 class="warning">WARNING</h3>
	<p>
	The following database names are reserved for use by SciSQL:
	</p>
	<dl>
		<dt>scisql</dt>
		<dd>Contains SciSQL stored procedures.</dd>
		<dt>scisql_test</dt>
		<dd>Used by SciSQL unit tests.</dd>
		<dt>scisql_demo</dt>
		<dd>Contains sample data that can be used to excercise the SciSQL UDFs.</dd>
	</dl>
	<p>
	The scisql and scisql_demo databases are dropped and re-created during
	installation. If you are using these databases for other things,
	you must migrate their contents to a different database prior to installing
	SciSQL. If you do not, <strong>YOU WILL LOSE DATA</strong>.
	</p>

	<h3>Configuration</h3>
	<p>
    	Run <tt>./configure</tt> from the top-level SciSQL directory. Passing <tt>--help</tt>
	will yield a list of configuration options. Here are the ones most likely to require
	tweaking:
	</p>
	<dl>
		<dt><tt>--prefix</tt></dt>
		<dd>Set this to the top-level MySQL server install directory.</dd>
		<dt><tt>--mysql-user</tt></dt>
		<dd>Set this to the name of a MySQL admin user</dd>
		<dt><tt>--mysql-socket</tt></dt>
		<dd>Set this to the name of the MySQL server UNIX socket file</dd>
	</dl>
	<p>
	You will be prompted for the MySQL admin user password during configuration.
	Connection details, including this password, are stored in
	<tt>build/c4che/.my.cnf</tt> in the MySQL options file format. This allows various
	build steps to connect to MySQL without constantly prompting for a password.
	</p>
	<p>
	Though the <tt>.my.cnf</tt> file permissions are set such that only the creator is
	allowed read/write access, for security reasons it is still recommended to
	run <tt>`make distclean`</tt> once sciSQL has been installed - this will remove the
	entire build directory and its contents.
	</p>

	<h3>Build/Install</h3>
	<p>
	SciSQL is built, installed, and uninstalled with the usual <tt>make</tt>,
	<tt>make install</tt>, and <tt>make uninstall</tt> commands.
	</p>
	<p>
TODO TODO TODO
	</p>
	</div>
</section>


<section name="s2" title="Spherical Geometry">
	<div class="section-docs">
	<p>
	TODO
	</p>
	</div>
</section>


<section name="photometry" title="Photometry">
	<div class="section-docs"><p>
	At the moment, these UDFs are limited to converting from raw fluxes to
	calibrated AB fluxes and magnitudes.
	</p></div>
</section>


<section name="statistics" title="Statistics">
	<div class="section-docs"><p>
	These UDFs provide the ability to compute medians and percentiles. Averages and 
	standard deviations can already be computed with the AVG and STDDEV SQL constructs.
	</p></div>
</section>


<section name="misc" title="Miscellaneous">
	<div class="section-docs"><p>
	These UDFs and stored procedures are either administrative, internal, or
	informational - they are not directly useful for scientific computation / queries.
	</p></div>
</section>

</sections>
